Guide to the Jonathan Hyman Photographs, 2002-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jonathan Hyman photographs 2002-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hyman, Jonathan.
6.0 linear feet Extent: 33 Items
Documentary photographer based in New York State. The color images in the Jonathan Hyman Photographs collection were taken by Hyman from 2002 to 2011, and portray vernacular memorials and other forms of public remembering that express anger, sadness and patriotic emotions following the 9/11 attack on the World Trade Centers and the Pentagon. Images take the form of graphic art, signs, sculpture, body art, and graffiti. Iconic elements include the U.S. flag, eagles, and the Twin Towers. Canvases for these forms of expression include clothing, buildings, vehicles, and tombstones. Most of the 33 large 20x24" inkjet prints were featured in Duke University exhibit Flesh & Metal, Bodies & Buildings: Works from Jonathan Hyman's Archive of 9/11 Vernacular Memorials, curated by Pedro Lasch. The exhibit was on display in the Rubenstein Photography Gallery from 9 May-16 October 2011. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
RL.00627
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Materials are to be used for educational, non-commercial use only; copyright is retained by creator.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jonathan Hyman Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Biographical Note
Photographer and Bethel, New York resident Jonathan Hyman graduated from Rutgers University where he was a Henry Rutgers Scholar. He holds a Master of Fine Arts degree from Hunter College and is best known for his ongoing documentary work surrounding the September 11th attacks. From the very day of the 9/11 attacks, Hyman has been photographing the vernacular artwork created by Americans on the side of the road and in public places in response to the attacks, as well as recording hundreds of oral histories. Hyman is also Associate Director for Conflict and Visual Culture initiatives at the Solomon Asch Center for Study of Ethnopolitical Conflict at Bryn Mawr College in Pennsylvania.
To mark the fifth anniversary of the terrorist attacks, Hyman’s work was featured in two museum exhibitions. The first, at Ground Zero in New York City, titled, 9/11 and the American Landscape: Photographs by Jonathan Hyman, was the first public programming organized by the National September 11 Memorial and Museum. The second exhibit, 9/11: A Nation Remembers, featuring 100 photographs, was at the National Constitution Center in Philadelphia. On the tenth anniversary of the attacks Hyman’s photographs will be exhibited in Duke University’s Special Collections Library and published by the University of Texas Press as A Photographer’s Journey: The Landscape of 9/11.
Hyman’s photographs have been featured in Time magazine, as well as many national and international publications. Beyond his well-known work on September 11 memorials, his areas of interest and expertise as a photographer fall under the rubric of Things Found on The Side of The Road, and they include: public memory, memorialization and speech, social class issues and visual public discourse, roadside commerce, urban street art, rural vernacular roadside art, and environmental concerns.
[Biography taken from Duke Libraries digital collections website, June 2012.]
Collection Overview
The color images in the Jonathan Hyman Photographs collection were taken by Hyman from 2002 to 2011, and portray vernacular memorials and other forms of public remembering that express anger, sadness and patriotic emotions following the 9/11 attack on the World Trade Centers and the Pentagon. Images take the form of graphic art, signs, sculpture, body art, and graffiti. Iconic elements include the U.S. flag, eagles, and the Twin Towers. Canvases for these forms of expression include clothing, buildings, vehicles, and tombstones. Most of the 33 large 20x24" inkjet prints were featured in Duke University exhibit Flesh & Metal, Bodies & Buildings: Works from Jonathan Hyman's Archive of 9/11 Vernacular Memorials, curated by Pedro Lasch. The exhibit was on display in the Rubenstein Photography Gallery from 9 May-16 October 2011. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Hyman, Jonathan; Documentary photography -- New York; Memorialization -- Social aspects; Patriotism -- United States -- Pictorial works; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001, in art; United States -- 21st century --Pictorial works; Color photographs
Contents of Collection
- Photographic Prints Series, 2002-2011, (2 boxes)
  Thirty-two 20x24" color inkjet exhibit prints and one 9x13" color print. The photographs were printed by the photographer on an Epson 9600 with Ultrachome inks on Ilford Galerie Smooth Pearl paper. Captions supplied by photographer.
  - T.C’s Back, Manhattan, New York, 2003 (Box 1, Image 1)
  - 9/11 Memorial Masks on Bicycle, Manhattan, New York, 2003 (Box 1, Image 2)
  - Bronx Parking Lot, Bronx, New York, 2003 (Box 1, Image 3)
  - Rest in Peace, Staten Island, New York, 2004 (Box 1, Image 4)
  - Tombstone with Towers: Cindy Ann Deuel, Paterson, New Jersey, 2004 (Box 1, Image 5)
  - Honor the Day, Manhattan, New York, 2003 (Box 1, Image 6)
  - Carnegie Hall Motorcycle, Manhattan, New York, 2002 (Box 1, Image 7)
  - Man Wearing Towers, Brooklyn, New York, 2005 (Box 1, Image 8)
  - Fighting Since 1492, Middletown, New York, 2006 (Box 1, Image 9)
  - Garbage Truck Tribute, Manhattan, New York, 2005 (Box 1, Image 10)
  - Brother Dave, Nashua, New Hampshire, 2006 (Box 1, Image 11)
  - 9/11: Seeing Red, Queens, New York, 2003 (Box 1, Image 12)
  - 7th Avenue Sheetrock Memorial, Manhattan, New York, 2002 (Box 1, Image 13)
  - Towers Go to Heaven, Bronx, New York, 2002 (Box 1, Image 14)
  - P.O.W./M.I.A. Tattoo, Randall's Island, New York City, New York, 2006 (Box 1, Image 15)
  - This Means War, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 2003 (Box 1, Image 16)
  - Ground Zero Memorial Bus, Manhattan, New York, 2006 (Box 2, Image 17)
  - Eagles, Brooklyn, New York, 2005 (Box 2, Image 18)
  - Bleeding Statue of Liberty, Manhattan, New York, 2002 (Box 2, Image 19)
  - Billy's Towers, Pinhurst, Massachusetts, 2006 (Box 2, Image 20)
  - Angry Hulk in the Pit, Queens, New York, 2003 (Box 2, Image 21)
  - Flag House, Kent, Connecticut, 2003 (Box 2, Image 22)
  - South Jersey Blimpie Base, Southern New Jersey, 2003 (Box 2, Image 23)
  - Firefighter Chan Rivera with Towers Tie, Grahamsville, New York, 2006 (Box 2, Image 24)
  - Jesus Holding the Towers, Brooklyn, New York, 2005 (Box 2, Image 25)
  - Flag, Eagle, Towers: Levittown Mural, Levittown, New York 2002 (Box 2, Image 26)
  - Special Agent Street Naming, Manhattan, New York, 2011 (Box 2, Image 27)
  - Borden Avenue Memorial, Queens, New York, 2006 (Box 2, Image 28)
  - Breezy Point Crosses, Queens, New York, 2005 (Box 2, Image 29)
  - Brocha's Memorial Tattoo, Manhattan, New York, 2006 (Box 2, Image 30)
  - COrned Beef Dinner, Forestburgh, New York, 2003 (Box 2, Image 31)
  - Woman With Arched Back, Bronx, New York, 2002 (Box 2, Image 32)
  - Flag Trees, Connecticut, 2003, (13"x19") (Box 2, Image 33)